this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
as a radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every two
weeks thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the program so welcome
listeners to this new episode of
software engineering radio this is once
again a language episode and as I think
mentioned a number of times before these
are some of my you know the episodes I
probably like most so this time we're
going to talk about closure and our
guest is well mister closure Richie key
hi hi thanks for being on the show well
why don't you introduce yourself before
we are talking about your creation
well Richie and I wrote closure closure
is a dynamic programming language for
the JVM it also runs on the CLR has sort
of four primary characteristics it's uh
it's it's a lisp it's it's designed to
be hosted so it has an intimate
relationship with the host platform you
know for instance the JVM it's mostly
functional so it has an emphasis on
immutability and pure functions and
immutable data structures and it has
another focus on concurrency so all the
aspects of the language were designed to
have meaningful semantics in the context
of a concurrent program okay and we're
going to explore that later I just
wanted to make our listeners aware that
we've had an episode on Lisp before I
just checked it was episode 84 with dick
Gabriel so while we were probably going
to talk about Lisp basics broadly or
briefly here we're not going to do a
full introduction to Lisp we probably
won't have the time so if you're not
familiar with Lisp Lisp at least you
know generally then you should go back
to episode 84 so I guess
nonetheless Richard would be a good idea
if you introduced a lisp basically what
are the fundamentals of Lisp how is this
different from other languages and and
maybe why is it special
many people would probably say okay well
that last point is probably the last
question is probably the best one
because you know many of the things that
Lisp innovated have you know become
available widely available in
programming languages I think I think
the thing that still makes Lisp unique
is that programs are presented to the
compiler in the forms of data structures
so a list compiler does not compile text
it compiles data structures and when you
do write a program in a lisp like
closure you write it in terms of writing
literal literal data structures so if
you do place text in a file what you do
is you you place the text that contains
data literals so but how is this
different from a programming language
that parses some kind of text and builds
an AST which is also data structure and
then feeds it into the compiler well it
has a lot to do with whether or not that
ast is made up of of the kinds of things
your program normally manipulates ah so
in in a lisp program and particularly in
closure the data literals are the things
that you use every day vectors and maps
and lists and so there's a huge library
of things for working with them it's not
a special library for working with an
AST tree it's the regular data
processing library of the language which
means that you don't need to write
special or unusual code to manipulate
the ast you write ordinary data
processing code so you could say that
programming and meta programming is the
same thing exactly they're no different
and and that really that really matters
I mean if you've ever worked with with
an ast library that presents an
object-oriented approach to an ast you
realize you're writing you know to a
very particular API and when you write
macros in closure or a lisp
you you're writing very ordinary data
structure processing code so what other
that the data
structures that are used you already
mentioned I think vectors and lists
right so you this program is basically a
set of nested lists so is that right and
that was true for lisps traditionally
for closure there are several other data
structures that have the same
first-class status as lists do okay that
would be vectors and maps returned alike
hash tables right and so there are forms
in the in the syntax of the language
which is again defined in terms of these
data structures that utilize vectors in
particular and sometimes maps so you
alluded to it and I guess it's also
obvious from episode 84 Lisp
isn't new Lisp is a quite old approach
and it has been used mmm successful in
some domains but it hasn't has never
really you know gotten mainstream so I
guess do you do you have an opinion why
it never got mainstream and then of
course the related question is why why
did you you know implement your own Lisp
in 2000 and I don't know eight nine or
ten well those are two separate
questions so no I did yeah why did list
never catch on as a mainstream language
I'm not sure it was designed to be a
mainstream language okay
I think at the time it came up it was it
was really designed around super you
know super users researchers and very
smart people who are trying to solve
very hard problems now and and Lisp
sort of maximally leveraged their
efforts you know you could sit in a lisp
environment and as an individual person
you had an incredible amount of power I
think we all know that programming and
the large is more of a social activity
now that involves other people it
involves libraries and it's particularly
critical to be able to interoperate with
things other people have done either in
the same or in different languages and
so that's an area where Lisp didn't do
as well traditionally because these
boxes and the approach were you know
there were like islands they were very
nice Island
with great pretty trees and beautiful
views yeah but not well connected I
would say to the rest of the world there
are some other you know social and and
historic reasons that have to do with
artificial intelligence and and it's its
demise in the 80s and 90s which and
being tied to that meant Lisp sort of
lost favor when AI did but it never lost
its power so to get to your second
question why would I do this today
the second half of the feature I wanted
to describe is still being unique to
Lisp is because the programs are
represented in data structures it means
you can write programs or write programs
and and the the second key aspect of a
Lisp is that when the compiler is
evaluating your program it gives your
other your macros which are also small
programs the opportunities to run during
the compilation process which means that
your program writing programs can be
integrated with the compiler yeah I
think that's that's a very important
aspect because it's really not a big
problem to write a program program that
uses let's say the the Eclipse ast API
to to graduate a Java program it might
not be as simple as lists but well I
guess that's a matter of taste
but the ability to plug it in into the
transformation or compilation process
that's and make it kind of seamless by
that that's that's important right so
that that enables a feature called
you know syntactic extensibility and
that's a powerful thing it's important
for programs in the same way that you
know function abstraction is important
you know we don't want to keep writing
the same things over and over again we
want to write them once and reuse them
and so there are many patterns and
software that can't be
well encapsulated by objects and methods
the simplest example would be in a Java
program you know the try block and the
kinds of yeah of frequently occurring
patterns that you have to write over and
over because you have no tools for
encapsulating them in something that
eliminates the repetition yeah so yeah
go ahead yes so that I consider that to
be an extremely valuable thing and worth
pursuing still so what I wanted to do
was make a list that retained what was
powerful about Lisp but addressed the
island problem yeah so so closure in
being in being hosted and and being on a
host not being an implementation detail
you know merely but but something that's
a feature and exposed is really
important and because that means that
now as a new language for instance
closure has full access to all the Java
libraries and it has a great ability to
interact with Java programs and you're
immediately off the island yeah yeah
well I'll get back to that later I just
want to return again to the briefly to
this meta programming stuff you said
that syntactic extensibility is an
important concern and an you know
measure of the power of a language like
Lisp now if I would play devil's
advocate I would say Lisp has no syntax
I mean if you represent everything as
lists then if and it's so far simple to
you know represent everything is lists
so and of course I'm exaggerating a
little bit but what I'm trying to get at
is is it in well the fact that Lisp is
so extensible regarding its syntax you
know the growing a language thing that
guy still had a while ago is that
because the syntax is so kind of trivial
and almost non-existent I mean it's not
so easy to be able to do that with Java
for example it independent of the meta
programming facilities so how important
is the syntactic simplicity to be able
to do what you described you know the
argument is that it's it's it's pretty
important
there aren't many meta programming
systems as easy to use as lisps I don't
think it's about list everything as a
list in fact everything is not on a list
in closure I know what you said it
before I'm exaggerating a little bit
and I think it's important because
there's a sense in which when everything
is a list it's actually a little bit
more complex right because that means
lists are more overloaded because there
is there is a syntax it's not actually
in the character representation very
much right the characters in issues
represent the data structures but then
there's a syntax in terms of you know
what is the interpretation of the data
structures and that's why their syntax
that's where the syntax lies more on
token level instead of on character
level if you will well yeah tokens and
and even bigger you know lists and and
nested vectors and things like that
right so that's where the syntax lies I
think the fact that that the syntax is
data structures and when you write a
transformer you produce new data
structures again is very simple
built in common data structures does
make the meta programming much much
simpler angry yeah so you you mentioned
that you know that the target audience
of classic lisps back then being the you
know the scientists who does AI stuff
who is the target audience of closure is
it really like Joe Java developer or is
it also you know do you think they would
like a lisp like language I mean who did
you target it at I I think any
programmer with a sufficiently open mind
will find working with a lisp a
thrilling and tremendously fun
experience that was my that was my
experience you know I had you know more
than a dozen years of C++ and Java and
c-sharp and Lisp is just tremendously
enabling and and I think that many of
the many people's initial reservations
about Lisp are are very superficial I
agree yeah because at the core for
instance closure is much much much
simpler than Java so once you can see
that you say wow this it's simpler and
potentially at least more succinct
but potentially more powerful
I guess there are though I think the
discussion that people have around this
is probably maybe that there are two
different notions of simplicity I mean
you could say that Lisp is simple
because it has a very simple syntax only
consisting of the couple of abstractions
you mentioned before and then it's very
orthogonal you can kind of you know
write code that writes code that writes
code and stuff but the other person
would say Java is simply because I'm
guided more I have more specific
language construct so I'm not I'm not so
out in the cold I'm much more you know
guided along a predefined path and that
can also be interpreted as some kind of
simplicity so I don't know what I'm
going to say whatever what I want well
you know I I think that most of that
people's simplicity there is a matter of
familiarity yeah I think when you take
somebody off the street and use and you
show them HelloWorld in Java yes if you
really try to explain every line of that
program yes you would realize how
complex Java is we've just comfortable
with that but it's not simple at all I
agree and I'm listening and when I'm
talking about the simplicity of a lisp
and and closure in particular I'm not
talking about syntactic simplicity
although that's there yeah talking about
the the lack of implicit complexity yeah
which is really where we suffer right
yeah I agree
I I have to say I I don't have any
practical experience with list with
lisps but I I can see what you're saying
and I would actually like to do some you
know spend four weeks and do something
meaningful with Lisp to to get some
experience two weeks ago we had a little
open space conference is about DSL and
we got together ten people talked about
different tools and languages and
facilities to build them in specific
languages and one person showed a couple
of lisp examples you know multi and
follows state machine example and Lisp
and it is very elegant so I can really
imagine or I can I can understand what
you're saying I just can't appreciate it
from my own experience that's why I
might sound a little bit skeptical but
it's it's really just I don't mean it
that way yeah I think you know I
I absolutely acknowledge the familiarity
aspect is important and it is an
impediment yeah that that people need to
get past if they're going to discover
what's possible yeah but it is more a
matter of familiarity than it is
simplicity yeah it's funny I have the
same I used the same arguments when I
try to convince people of let's say
using MPs projection on editor to write
code instead of a normal SK editor and I
also say you have to believe that at the
other end everything wrasse is much much
greener and you have to go through this
pain so I guess it's the yeah yeah so
what's different from normal lisps or
classical lists you already mentioned
the fact that it's very well integrated
and explicitly integrated with the VM
and I guess we will talk about that in a
minute
but from a language perspective what's
different from from lisps - two things
are the primary differences one is in
traditional lisps the core data
structures are mutable okay so they have
you know con cells to represent lists
and and people should be aware that you
know like Common Lisp has vectors and it
has a raise and it has hash tables and
and you know all the a monitor
structures if they're all mutable so
that's an area where for instance
because I wanted the prime data
structure is primary data structures to
be immutable I couldn't retrofit closure
on top of say scheme or common list
right the second area in which closure
differs is that you know Lisp is very
old and yes and scheme is very old and
they actually predate some modern
concepts like interfaces and and
polymorphic API design yeah because they
you know they came from Lisp innovated
in areas as simple as having the
unconditional yes so so closure has an
API design that's built upon
abstractions so we're in a traditional
Lisp you know there's a library
functions for dealing with lists they
really were hardwired to a particular
data structure similarly there were you
know you know functions for doing with
vectors and with maps and
they were they work specifically with
the concrete data structure was supplied
with the language enclosure there are
abstractions behind all of the data
structures and all of the library code
is written in terms of these
abstractions so you can imagine them to
be Java interfaces right and they are in
fact Java interfaces under the hood that
means that the entire sequence library
works with anything that's remotely
sequential or or could provide a
sequential view and that's a big deal
because now you get a far greater
leverage out of library code right than
you would otherwise
so those are the two biggest differences
that the the core data structures are
immutable and the built in libraries
built in terms of abstractions and not
concrete data structures and I guess so
I mean Common Lisp at object-orientation
although in a somewhat different way
than we typically know it from
mainstream languages today do you have
that - can you define classes in in
enclosure and and how are they different
from Java classes or maybe they aren't
so so how do you go about that there are
there are sort of two things that you
can do one is you can define classes and
interfaces that are in fact Java classes
and interfaces and that's there for
interoperability it's also there as an
abstraction tool in the becoming
versions of closure there are these
things I call protocols which are
they're kind of like Java interfaces
with the benefit being that you could
extend an existing class for which you
do not you know over which you don't
have control to participate in a
protocol where as an interface requires
you derive and so that will be the main
abstraction mechanism that's still not
an object-oriented system for closure in
the same respects as you traditionally
think of objects I mean most people
think of objects as mutable state 'full
yes things and so this closure still
will provide that except via the Java
Interop okay so the basic abstractions
you
going to create enclosures basically
data structures and functions that work
on them
correct but with protocols you still
have the ability to define sets of
functions as abstractions with names and
get polymorphic behavior right okay I
like polymorphism and I think it can be
you know pried out of object orientation
and delivered Alucard so in that sense
those those protocols would kind of act
as an adapter then to other data
structures that don't yet implement the
behavior directly they are like adapters
except they do not require wrappers ah
okay so there's some compiler magic
going on yeah okay which leads me to the
question which I kind of already
answered it's compiled right it's not
interpreted correct there's no
interpreter in closure so I you still
get dynamic code loading and you have a
repple it's just that everything is
compiled as it's loaded repple means
read eval print loop right right really
well print that's interactive you know
yeah interface yeah so have you done any
performance measurements comparing a
closure with say Java yeah yeah in terms
of calling normal methods closure is the
same speed as Java time it's the same
bytecode right okay the big performance
difference with Java is that enclosure
in in normal closure code numbers are
always boxed so you're always getting
the bigeye integer happy go long
so that has performance overhead and
that and obviously math with that is
slower arithmetic with that is slower
yeah
however inside a function you can
declare our primitives let you know int
and long and exactly the same as Java
and the arithmetic with those can be
made you know the same as Javas right of
course there are different levels you
know by default a lisp has automatic
promotion of integers to as large a data
type as is required
the result now and closure offers three
flavors of arithmetic one one that does
that one that does native primitive
arithmetic but with overflow checking
which is still safe yeah and the third
kind is you know essentially bad job it
does I mean Java has silent overflows
all right if you want that that's the
fastest possible thing and it's
available enclosure mm-hmm okay so I
guess we should talk a little bit about
closures approach to concurrency because
first of all I guess concurrency is an
interesting topic these days in general
and you said that that was a motivation
or was one of the important
characteristics of closure so I guess
one aspect of you know being concurrency
friendly is the thing you mentioned
before conquer immutable data structures
right can you canal can you elaborate
briefly on that sure I would I would
definitely want to start start there you
know I think in the broadest sense
closures approach to data structures and
object orientation and concurrency all
are all tied together and they have to
do with they're all born of a
frustration of dealing with state ok yes
all your talk about time right I I think
this Keuka nor where was it sure that
was at the jvm language time language
assignment okay yeah right so yeah I
mean that that's what's really that's
what closure is really about you know
even if you don't have concurrency I
think that large object-oriented
programs struggle with with increasing
complexity as you build this large
object graph of mutable objects in in
really you know trying to understand and
keep in your mind what will happen when
you call a method and what will the
side-effects be and you know where will
it have impact so and that's just simply
because things have side-effects or are
you referring to something more more
more unknown
more strange no I'm talking about
mutable object right okay as simple a
thing as you know if you're given a
mutable object you know can you maintain
a reference to it yeah as the value you
know can you go back to it later and
know that it will be the same value
represent the same value those concepts
are are merged together in
object-oriented programming languages
and and there's a sense in which that's
broken I think what you would you called
it in your your presentation at the
language of Summit was the distinction
between state and identity am I correct
correct okay yeah that's right so the
entity remains the same over time but
the state and the value of something
changes correct and if you're able to
obtain those values it means that you're
able to make a huge portion of your
program independent of the identities
and and the change part so in other
words you would star values and not
identities that's right you can remember
values quite easily and you can form
computations on them without worry yeah
and and we should do that more and you
know I think the fact that when we start
in an object-oriented language and we
make a class and we get mutable fields
by default where we we have far more
mutation than we require yeah and it
takes an incredible amount of discipline
to to remove that yeah so closure takes
the opposite approach and says you know
let's start with programming with values
which don't change and do as much as we
can with that and then and only then
when we need you know an identity we'll
deal with that independently again
trying to make orthogonal decisions
about about things so so we start with
how do we program with values mm-hmm
which goes to your first question which
is you know what you know how do you
represent things that are bigger than
you know numbers and strings as as
values you need efficient data
structures for representing collections
for instance as values or even small
ones that would have been objects and so
closure comes with the suite of data
structures that are
they're called persistent data
structures persistence doesn't have
anything to do with being stored on a
desk in this case what persistence means
is that a data structure is immutable it
means that if you were going to do
something that would change it what
you're really going to do is produce a
new version of it basically excuse me a
copy basically copy paint well no no
because then the next the next feature
of a persistent data structure is that
the data structures have performance
guarantees you know the Big O guarantees
that you would expect okay
so if the Big O guarantee of a data
structure is that you can add something
to it in log n time but let me let me
try to say it differently
it feels semantically like a copy but
it's not a brute-force duplication of
the data structure but there is rather
some more clever stuff going on exactly
that that's the real key and the thing
is it needs to be said because people's
first intuition is that this will
require copying yes and that can't be
made efficient and that that's not
what's happening so persistent data
structures you make a new version the
new version can be made while meeting
the performance guarantees so that
already implies that it's not a copy if
a promise login and you it had to copy
that would be linear time yes the other
attributes of a persistent data
structure is that the old version is
still available it's not destroyed nor
is it degraded so the performance of the
old version is as good as it ever was
because there are schemes for for doing
persistence that sort of have the old
versions degrade over time by I don't
know why because it because of the way
the structural sharing might work okay
so so the first-class persistent data
structure the old versions are as good
as the latest version okay and when you
have all of those things you have a
completely different you know tool in
your hand for doing programming
remembering values is easy storing you
know undo stacks is cheap doing
speculative work in a recursive fashion
is inexpensive
and dealing with concurrency is easy
because these values are immutable they
don't require any locking or anything
else to be used in a concurrent context
so I guess it's worth spending five more
minutes on this persistent data
structure thing because I kind of almost
forget about it and as you hit remember
it's not in there it's not in the agenda
but it's a very important point so so
assume I have let's say an expression
just to make it simple I have an
expression that multiplies two with the
product with the sum of two other
numbers like two times three plus four
just so we have some kind of tree like
data structure okay you know I replace
the the four you know the two times
three plus four I replace the four with
a five so trivially I'd have to copy the
whole data structure and that's not
what's going on so can you briefly
explain how this magic works so that you
get a copy and don't copy well if we
take the the simplest persistent data
structure would be a singly linked list
so if if if I had a singly linked list
that was a B and C and and you wanted to
prepend yeah you know act X you could
make a new node write X and you could
have its tail point to my list right in
that case it's trivial yes I agree right
so but the important note there is that
they're structural sharing write your
list shares its tail with my entire list
and because I can never change anything
that can never be a problem regarding
you know something changed over here
exactly that's so that's the other
that's the other key thing is that
because I can't change my list yes right
I can't I can't harm your list right
right right right
so to scale this concept to any other
data structure you move from a list to a
tree yep and basically all of the
closure data structures that would be
you know hash hash Maps or vectors are
represented as trees mm-hmm so as soon
as you've got it represented as a tree
it means that you know you only need to
copy the path to the part of the tree
that you're changing right as opposed to
the
entire tree for instance if you
represented a vector as an array yeah
you would have no hope but to have to
copy the entire array I mean in some
sense you can see a tree as a set and as
a number of linked lists in the sense
that every note doesn't just have one
tail but many tails and that gives you a
tree you can of course the
implementation doesn't work that not
mentally right exactly well that's
that's why I started with the list price
it is essentially it's your you have
chains of things right and this is you
have a tree structure then modifying any
leaf in the tree it only requires
copying the path to the root right and
nothing else and the new tree shares
everything with the old tree except that
one path so closures data structures are
trees of arrays and so they have a very
high branching factor and they're very
shallow and that ends up being very fast
okay that's how they work good so so I
guess that's the the whole thing about
immutability which again if you don't
share anything that is mutable you don't
have to lock so you remove all the
locking issues immediately right but
then of course people will say that if
you never change anything
how how sensibly can a program be so I
guess at some point you need to be able
to change some things I mean a database
is something that changes so how do you
deal with I mean do you deal with data
that changes and if so how yes well that
that's really the key that's the key
thing about closure is that it makes no
attempt and it doesn't purport to say
that you could write programs with only
pure functions and immutable data yeah
because they you know realistic programs
that operate over extended periods of
time and get input from the outside
world and interact with the outside
world do have state yeah so so how do
you do that and the key the key thing is
to realize the difference between the
value and and and the the notion of an
identity right which is something you
might talk about over time so the
example I'll use here is imagine a
program that has people log in and out
over the
course of its running the set of logged
in users is it is a collection in a
traditional program you might consider
that to be something that's mutable the
collection itself right so when somebody
logs in you would actually you know
change that collection and that ends up
being a big problem because now you have
the possibility that somebody was
looking at the old version and iterating
over it and now they get a concurrent
you know a modification exception yeah
or you so then you have all these
difficulties so but what's really
happening is that there's this identity
which is that the thing you're naming
right the set of logged in users you
have an idea and at any particular point
in time it has a value so if you
represent those values as immutable
collections then all you really need to
do is ensure sequential of a sequential
relationship between the idea of the set
of logged in users and a particular set
a particular value okay and that that
only requires a little atomic data
structure right which is a reference to
the value and you can give and that's
the thing who's whose contents change so
let me try to recap you you closure
provides something called an atom right
that's one of the possible thing yes
right and an atom is a wrapper around a
value where of course the value in the
wrapper can change over time it provides
an identity and it ensures sequential
access to the repped data right right so
I would I would take that one level
higher so atom is an example of one of
closures variants type one of closures
reference types and so the reference
types are all about the same problem
they're about giving you a tool for
representing identity and giving you a
tool for managing time and the
succession of states associated with an
identity okay give us an example how
does that work so you can imagine these
ref
is to be a little box mm-hmm right and
and in the box is a value and by value
we mean something that can't change so
the set of logged in users will be a box
inside the box at any particular point
in time will be an immutable set data
structure mm-hm and when you want to add
a user you're going to take that
immutable value you're gonna call a
function on it produce another immutable
value which is that set with one more
user in it and want to associate that
new value with the identity which is the
set of logged in you okay but but if two
people do that at the same time from
different threats than you run into
concurrency issues except that these
reference types have concurrency
semantics AHA that's their job okay so
so the the trick is to separate the two
problems so we're no longer talking
about the problem of actually modifying
a collection to put another thing in it
yep that's it those are functions on
values what we have really are left with
is just a problem of saying how do we go
from one state to the next where each
state is a value okay with that without
colliding with each other and how do
this go ahead yeah go ahead I was just
gonna say how does this feel from an API
perspective I mean what do I do I mean I
have I have such an atom here one of
those reference data types okay and I
want to hobble to do so if you have
really any of the reference types they
all have the same shape to the
interaction and there is a single model
for for changing state and that is given
some reference in which there's a value
you want to change you're going to pass
that reference a function which is a
function of the value that's in there
okay possibly some additional arguments
the reference type itself is responsible
for taking the function you've given it
and applying it to the value and making
the return value of that function the
next state of that reference right and
the reference tab makes sure that only
one of these functions is executed at
any time correct so
of course this implies that you have to
have first-class functions in your
language yeah right so you can pass a
function yep in in and then then there
are different semantics possible for how
and when the change will occur so the
change could be synchronous or it could
not be synchronous right
you could you could ask for functions to
be applied to the value and want to know
when the that call returns that it's
happened yeah or you'd be happy to say
please do this eventually and go on that
would be the asynchronous case yeah so
there are differences there there are
differences with whether or not the the
change you want to make impacts only one
reference or involves the coordination
of changing more than one reference okay
so then you have probably another
wrapper around those that coordinates it
well there are different kinds of
references that have the different
semantics and now we could talk about
the three main kinds okay atoms are the
simplest they're synchronous and their
atomic they can only a unit of work and
only involve one atom at a time right
agents are like atoms they're atomic
you can only impact one agent at a time
but they're asynchronous so when you
send an agent a function that will
happen at some point in the future that
call returns immediately okay and the
agent will process all the actions
they're called that it's been sent in in
a thread pool sometime later but it will
ensure that they're performed serially
and finally the most complex reference
type is is actually called a ref and a
ref can only be changed inside a
transaction ah okay and refs are both
synchronous and they're coordinated so
you can have a unit of work that
involves more than one ref which is what
you would need for instance in order to
take something out of one collection and
put it into another collection so you
would open up front a transaction and
modify the two refs within it
correct okay so this is a nice system in
that you've sort of you've moved
everything into pure functions so what
you want for instance to test your
function for adding something to a set
you don't have any state you don't have
to mock up anything you don't have to
create a certain state in the world
because that's a pure function so
testing that your functions is all very
simple they don't involve the state and
then you have the separate problem of
okay well now I want to send that
function into one of the reference types
to be performed safely in a concurrent
environment so the two problems have
been separated and that you can make all
these different semantics look exactly
the same they all look precisely the
same the the state transition models are
all identical pass a function to the
reference yeah so so that's why one
buzzword that I hear around closure is
that it has transactional memory that's
exactly this this thing this last the
last kind of reference ties to the rest
are implemented using right
transactional memory right okay and I
guess we've had an episode on this topic
before also I didn't look up the number
so you have to find that out for
yourself so yeah up although I would say
that closures approach to software
transactional memory is very different
okay from what you might see in papers
and in in discussions about software
transactional memory in which way a lot
of people are working on software
transactional memory with the objective
of allowing you to take your existing
code that manipulates objects mutable e
yeah just wrap that with transactions in
order to eliminate needing to do locking
I personally am not fond of that
approach I don't think it's going to
work this approach I've mentioned with
closures is very different I mean it
emphasizes programming with values right
in using pure functions emphasizes using
values for aggregates so the granularity
is much coarser yeah and and it uses
multi-version concurrency control under
the hood so it's it's pretty different
and you also expose the fact that
some data is mutable through
transactions to the programmer so you
don't attempt any kind of transparency
no I think transparency is bad yeah I
would probably agree here right so right
so wouldn't I mean I mean okay I'm kind
of putting words into your mouth now
assuming that this reasonable support
for time values identity in concurrency
has been one of the main drivers for
building closure wouldn't if wouldn't it
have been possible or simpler to attach
to add this using you know some kind of
library of framework to an existing
language in other words why does this
kind of stuff need language support as
opposed to just a library in fact it is
a library okay it's a library written in
Java that you can use from Java okay the
whole thing about a language is you know
what a language is about what does it
make idiomatic and easy so for instance
you can use precisely the same reference
types and the STM and the data
structures of closure all from Java yeah
of course but you'll die because you
have to write all kinds of an anonymous
inner classes to represent the functions
right there's the function apart right
there's the lack of in Ematic library
support yeah for you know for instance
with programming with values you have to
reassign them to something so that's not
idiomatic right and so the lack of
idioms and and language support means
using exactly the same constructs the
same underlying code from Java yeah is
extremely painful compared to closure
where it's it is the natural idiom yeah
and and it's what you're doing by
default I mean when you use closure and
you use closures data structures you're
programming this way always yeah it's
not something you superimpose later and
and with that's a good thing because
when you discover you need or desire you
know to add concurrency
you don't have to change everything in
your program you're already doing the
right thing
actually I really liked your definition
of foreign languages because I struggled
with that all the time since I work a
lot with domain-specific languages and
people always ask me what's the
difference between a language and an API
and why do I need the language I can
express everything with you know insert
X whatever here and this thing about
making things
idiomatic or or making the right things
simple to express right that's that's a
very good definition right yeah so that
that's the key thing and that's why all
these independent pieces of closure you
know are designed together to make all
the different parts you know work well
one last technical question before we
probably talked about more community and
adoption stuff another way of handling
state in purely functional immutable
languages are monads I think we've
talked about this concept before an
essay radio in Eric Myers episode I
think does this play a role in your your
closure language thing um there are
libraries for that I think that monads
don't fundamentally solve the identity
problem mm-hmm in other words you can't
use a monad for the set of logged in
users a long-running program across
multiple parts of your program
yeah all right and and that's why
Haskell has an ST m and M VARs it has
those things because that's how you get
multiple independent threads of control
to coordinate a monad is about one
thread of tribal no one has nothing to
do with concurrency yes correct and so
so so you can't use the same construct
for the two different jobs in Haskell so
I'm not sure that's always going to be
the right construct then also its while
there are libraries for closure I think
the concept is much more powerful in a
language like Haskell where the type
system is yes helping a lot yeah I mean
maybe that was my question is your type
system aware of monads and and so the
answer is no it's automatic to use them
no no of course with macros I mean it
can be okay yeah but the the main thing
that has
skill has going for it is that you know
because it can do inference on return
types yeah
and that's a particularly critical
feature for monads
closures dynamically typed right so then
there is the you wouldn't be able to do
the mona type inference thing anyway
right well it closure does do local
inferencing for instance you know in
order to get to get to get calls to Java
to work without reflection yeah we'd
need to know the types yeah but you'll
find in closure you need to specify far
fewer types than you would in Java
because once it knows a little bit its
able to infer the result of this calls
of this type which means this next call
is taking this type of arguments et
cetera et cetera
so then is it duck typed or is it
statically typed those are that's a
binary choice well but if it's if it's
if it's well I mean type inference done
by the compiler I wouldn't call that
duck typing I would just called it a
compiled language Auto statically
checked with with with with in type
inference support so well their
differences are they come down to
enforcement right so if I can figure out
through inference what's happening
I can generate better code yes if I
can't I'm not gonna preclude it which
means that you'll get on collective code
at runtime ever which may discover that
you know there's no method with that
name okay but that means that I can
specify type information in closure and
if it's present I get statically
compiled code as opposed to the
reflection based code again moverá
precise you will get code that's
compiled with particular types and runs
exactly identical to Java yes on the
other hand you won't get a code that
precludes you passing different types
okay in other words it's not it's not a
mechanism it's a mechanism only for
optimization right okay that's not we're
not for precluding a certain expression
okay but that's like checking but you
can specify types and then the compiler
uses them to generate more efficient
code assuming they're correct right for
the Java interrupt portion
ah okay mm-hmm good is there anything
technical about the language that I
forgot to ask that you would like to
mention
yeah like cool language features you
know technical as opposed to adoption
community where can people no no I mean
I think actually at the at the core of
closure technically it's very very very
simple and and in fact that that would
be the the biggest thing I'd want people
to understand about it is that it's it
is extremely simple and it's
computational core there's not there are
not a lot of rules there are not a lot
of syntactic things there is and it's
less even about syntax a it really
computationally is extremely simple okay
so then let's talk about the soft stuff
so how is closure doing regarding
adoption and in the general let's say
language zoo that has developed on the
JVM in the last two or three years III
think it's doing remarkably well
considering its the most recent entry
the mailing list on Google Groups is now
up to three thousand three hundred
members so this pretty significant
adoption and utilization there people
are now getting jobs in closure it's
being used by companies and it started
in startups but it's definitely seeing
some applications in other areas for
analytics and various other things
financial news and there are any typical
usage scenarios I mean you know things
for which the way closure works is
especially while concurrency I guess but
it's especially well-suited uh well you
know what I think what one of the great
things for me to have seen is that you
know it was designed to be a
general-purpose language and it's seeing
wide applications and vastly different
okay I mean okay one area I if I were to
try to pick something out that seems
seems to me to be the first area that's
kind of hot
would be like the flight caster use of
closure which they used it for machine
learning running on you know Hadoop
button on clusters and their libraries
have been integrated with some other
statistical libraries for closure called
in canter and it seems to be a hot area
now where people doing analytics that
would traditionally have used R and then
had to hand their code to programmers to
move into production could use closure
to do that work to work with large data
from the get-go you know and to be able
to hand their models directly to people
that you know for use in production so
that's an area that seems to be booming
but it's also been used for web stuff
and database stuff and messaging systems
and but but it's probably fair to say
that it can play out its benefits
especially well if it's a growth maclean
non-trivial concurrent stuff there is
that although I think you might find
that the the concurrency part is used
less often and you might imagine I I
wouldn't say that that's it's it's only
trick it's an extremely expressive
language and and and it does let you tap
into the JVM you know ecosystem so
there's a huge number of libraries
available and people are extremely
productive with it and that I think is
what's what matters so a book is
available right by Stewart hell away yes
so people can read that yeah there were
two two more books on the way okay and
they can get early access versions from
Manning one is called closure in action
and the other one is called the joy of
closure and are you writing one of those
nope no okay I'm surprised I mean I
might enclosure okay well maybe
at some point but so far I'm too busy
okay well I guess that's that's a good
sign I mean okay so so yeah so the
community is great the mailing list is
is large we always have let me see right
now we have 232 people on the IRC Wow
Channel these are other just kind of
metric things so it's a it's easy to get
help
everybody's very friendly it's easy to
get started good cool
very nice so I guess the only problem
quote problem is to find a customer at
least in my case who who would want me
to use closure instead of mainstream
stuff
which is I guess at least in some
environments still a challenge I guess
to convince none you know but the
somewhat more conservative people well
tell me you want to use this new java
library called closure yes it comes in a
jar like all the others yeah good trick
yeah yeah no I mean the adoption will
play out at different rates in different
industries that you know depending on
the level of you know conservatism and
you know what people are doing and but
it has been interesting to see it used
pretty widely already it's their tool
support you know ID use syntax
highlighting and that kind of stuff
absolutely the it's a it's actually
really good there's a of course does
eMac support if you're if you like Emacs
and it's traditionally been a great
place for Lisp but if you like more
traditional hi des there's a very good
support for NetBeans it's a project
called enclosure which is it's great it
has completion for closure and Java you
know very good integration with Java
syntax highlighting the ripples built
into the IDE equal
similarly IntelliJ has good closure
support you know closures a recognized
project type it's a you know it comes
from the IntelliJ guys and they've done
a really good job somewhat newer and
less developed but up and coming is a
clip support
so a bunch of a bunch of options I guess
if you have those three then you're set
yeah yeah and and then of course closure
participates in the general
infrastructure for by code on the JVM so
debuggers and profilers for java work
with closure on source code level yeah
cool very good okay I guess that's all I
had prepared is there anything else you
want to add or no I would just encourage
people to try it out yep yep and for
sure you know join the join the Google
group and in the IRC if you're trying it
out and this there's plenty of help cool
very good so then thank you very much
for being on the show thanks for having
me
bye-bye thanks for listening to software
engineering radio software engineer
radio is an educational program brought
to you by hillside Europe if you want
more information about the podcast and
all the other episodes visit our website
at se - radio dotnet if you want to
support us you can donate to the SU
radio team via the website or you can
advertise for se radio for example by
clicking on the Digg reddit delicious
links and the slash dot button to
contact the team please send email to
team @ s e - radio net or if you're
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under the
Creative Commons
two-point-five license please see the
website for details thanks to Charlie
Crowell and the pot site Music Network
for the music used in this show the song
is called Vegas
[Music]